You may have heard
the expression
“knowledge is power.”
Well, today we’re going
to give you more power
to control your
diet and lifestyle
by giving you the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we conclude our series
on how industries impact
dietary and health guidelines.
Did you know that the
meat industry’s own study
concluded that meat consumption
increased the risk of cancer,
heart disease, diabetes,
and premature death.
Here’s the story.
A series of papers published
in the Annals of Internal Medicine
that largely discounted all but the
highest quality randomized studies
reached a conclusion directly
contrary to the public health advice
we've heard for years. They
suggested that we should
continue our current consumption
of both red and processed meat.
The authors based their exclusion
of evidence on the so-called GRADE
criteria, which were mainly developed
for evaluating evidence from drug trials.
We need randomized double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials for drugs,
but strictness of these criteria would
probably cause evidence for just about
every dietary, lifestyle, and
environmental factor related
to chronic disease to be graded
as "low" or "very low" evidence.
If the GRADE criteria were used
to evaluate the evidence
for other factors related to diet,
such as inadequate fruits
and vegetables or too
much soda or alcohol,
or whether or not exercise
is good, or safe sex,
or sleep, smoking, air pollution,
none of the current recommendations
on these issues would be supported
by high- or even moderate-quality
evidence using the drug trial criteria.
But even after ignoring major
parts of the available evidence,
they still found an association
between meat intake
and an increased risk of cancer.
And not just cancer.
They found that adherence to dietary
patterns lower in red or processed meat
intake may result in a decreased risk
for premature death, cardiometabolic
disease and mortality, meaning the
risk of getting and dying of diseases
like heart disease and type 2 diabetes,
as well as the risk of getting
cancer and dying from cancer.
Yet, they still concluded in their
dietary guideline recommendations:
continue your current
red meat consumption,
continue your processed
meat consumption.
Forget the whole premature death
thing, cancer, heart disease, diabetes—
just keep eating your
burgers and bacon.
So you have these dietary guidelines
developed by some self-appointed panel
that are tantamount to
promoting meat consumption,
despite their own findings that high
consumption is harmful to health.
How did they square that,
contradicting the evidence generated
from their own meta-analyses?
There's only one body of evidence.
They found the same risk that
all the other reviews found.
So they're not saying meat
is less risky; they're just saying
the risk is acceptable. Well, you do
have to consider the risk and benefits.
Well, we've covered the harms.
Their own data show that a moderate
reduction in red and processed meat
consumption can reduce total mortality
by 13%, heart disease mortality by 14%,
cancer mortality by 11%, and
type 2 diabetes risk by 24%.
What are the benefits? In short,
omnivores enjoy eating meat.
Uh, okay...
Given peoples' attachment
to their meat-based diet,
the associated risk reduction
in our leading killers, like cancer,
heart disease, diabetes, is not
likely to provide sufficient motivation
to reduce consumption of
red meat or processed meat.
So therefore, eat up!
In fact, they even say straight out that
unlike the other dietary guidelines
suggesting we limit consumption of
stuff because of like the cancer thing,
these other guidelines have paid
little or no attention to the reasons
people eat meat,
whereas they did a systematic review
of preferences regarding meat
consumption, and people who
eat meat enjoy eating meat.
Maybe that's even why they do it.
They're generally unwilling to
change their meat consumption,
even in response to health concerns,
so the panel believed —
the panel, you'll remember,
with generous support of a group
getting millions every year
from the meat industry —
the panel believed that for
the majority of individuals,
the desirable effects, like
lowering your risk
of family-devastating
cancer and heart attacks
associated with reducing meat
consumption probably do not outweigh
the undesirable effects, like having
to give up all that yummy meat.
This is what led them to
make their recommendation
to "continue current consumption."
That sounds like something straight
of the journal, Meat Science.
Why should we keep eating red meat?
Because of the enjoyment.
People also like to smoke.
They like to drink soda.
They like to have unsafe sex.
It's kind of like saying we know
motorcycle helmets can save lives,
but some people still prefer the
feeling of the wind in their hair.
So let's just tell people
to not wear helmets?
But you'll actually
see this argument.
Complying with dietary recommendations
imposes a "taste cost" on consumers,
so how about socially desirable
dietary recommendations
that are most compatible
with consumer preferences,
you know, that best balance health
benefits against "taste cost."
So like hey, even if science told us
that eating butter is unhealthy,
its taste justifies the
continuation of using it.
What do you expect from NutriRECS,
the meat-industry-partnered panel
that also published the paper
criticizing the sugar guidelines,
funded by the soda
and candy industries?
They aim to produce nutritional
guideline recommendations
based on the
preferences of patients.
So what's next? Just telling people to
eat doughnuts and ice cream all day?
Yet the Annals published the meat
papers with a press release saying,
"No need to reduce red or processed
meat consumption for good health."
Using the same
methodology and rationale,
they might as well have said,
"No need to quit smoking
for good health" or
"No need to exercise
for good health."
As Dr. Katz, Director of Yale's
Prevention Research Center put it,
"Guidelines opposing the very data
on which they purport to be based
are not science;
they are anti-science."
In our next story,
Big Meat downplays the
magnitude of meat mortality.
Across the board,
a series of studies
published in the Annals
of Internal Medicine, found
a statistically significant association
between lower consumption
of red and processed meats
and lower total mortality,
meaning living a longer life,
lower cardiovascular
disease mortality,
as well as lower risk
of dying from cancer.
Yet remarkably, the authors
of these studies concluded
that people should ignore all
the other dietary guidelines, and
keep eating meat to their heart's
content — or rather discontent.
They offered three reasons why their
panel reached a conclusion at odds
with other contemporary dietary
guidelines that advise people
to cut down on meat.
One reason is taste.
In short, people who enjoy
eating meat, enjoy eating meat.
I did a whole video on this.
But in short, taste preference
probably shouldn't be a major factor
in developing dietary guidelines.
Many people don't want to quit smoking,
stop drinking, or exercise more,
but that doesn't change the science;
it shouldn't change the public
health recommendations.
A second reason they explain
why their recommendations differ
from everyone else's is that
other guidelines didn't use
the so-called GRADE approach.
No wonder, since GRADE was
mainly developed for evaluating
evidence from drug trials.
There are grading systems for
diet and lifestyle approaches,
but the meat panel chose
to inappropriately apply GRADE,
which could similarly be misused
to undermine recommendations
about tobacco, air pollution,
trans fats, you name it.
I've got three videos delving
deep into all that, but this video
is about the third reason they give
for ignoring meat reduction advice.
Other guidelines didn't highlight
the very small magnitude
of the meat effects.
In other words, even if meat
does cause heart disease,
cancer, diabetes, and death,
it doesn't cause that
many heart attacks,
doesn't kill that many people,
cause that much cancer to
offset all the juicy taste benefits.
Of course, it matters what
people replace the meat with.
Replacing even 3% of calories from
animal protein with plant protein
is linked to living longer,
but eggs were the worst.
Yes, replacing red meat protein
with plant protein sources
may lower overall mortality
more than 10%,
but getting rid of egg protein
and we're talking more than 20%
lower risk of premature death.
So if someone reduces meat
consumption by swapping a burger
for an egg salad sandwich,
that particular reduction in meat
could mean more mortality.
But maybe they concluded there was
such a small effect only because
major bodies of evidence were omitted,
and relevant studies excluded
because the authors
didn't like the results.
It's not that there aren't tons
of randomized controlled trials
about meat; it's just that
they appeared to cherry pick
a few to fit their agenda,
discarded studies that
even met their own criteria,
and wrongly rejected randomized
controlled trials clearly showing
that meat increased risk factors
like cholesterol or blood pressure.
Like why wasn't PREDIMED
included, or the literally hundreds
of randomized trials
on the DASH diet?
What about the Lyon Diet
Heart Study, which involved
randomizing individuals to
a more Mediterranean diet
with significant drop
in meat consumption?
Compared to the control group,
they experienced a 70% reduction in
mortality from all causes put together.
Why did they exclude that study?
They excluded it because,
in their words,
it "reported an implausibly
large treatment effect."
In other words, it worked too well.
No surprise, given that this so-called
NutriRECS meat panel was partnered
with, and had multiple people on
the payroll of, Texas A&M Agrilife,
which receives literally millions
of dollars of meat industry
money every year.
So you probably won't be shocked to
find out they also excluded research
comparing health outcomes
of vegetarians to meat eaters.
As they described it, they were
interested in realistic decreases
in meat consumption, like cutting
down three servings a week.
In fact, the study that
they mostly relied on,
the Women's Health Initiative,
achieved only a difference of
1.4 servings of meat per week.
That could be like a half
an ounce difference
in meat consumption per day,
about a fifth of a hamburger.
Participants in the Women's
Health Initiative reduced
meat intake only modestly,
resulting in a modest reduction in
mortality related to breast cancer.
This finding in no way supports
the notion that there's no need
to reduce red or processed meat
consumption for good health.
Rather, it shows that modest
dietary changes yield modest benefits.
As an analogy, if studies showed that
modest reductions in tobacco use
yielded only modest health benefits,
it would be inaccurate and dangerous
to suggest that there's no need to
reduce tobacco use for good health.
To say that small increases
in meat consumption
only cause small increases
in the risk of disease
doesn't mean that eating
meat is good for you.
That's like saying that smoking 24
cigarettes a day increases your risk
of lung cancer only a little more
than smoking 20 cigarettes a day —
being careful not to include any
studies that compared smoking
24 to smoking none — and
then erroneously concluding
that smoking isn't that
bad for your health.
Despite all that, despite the ignoring
evidence, excluding evidence,
the meat panel nonetheless
found entirely consistent,
clinically meaningful,
statistically significant
adverse effects of eating more
meat and processed meat
on all-cause mortality,
on cardiovascular disease,
on cancer, and on diabetes.
"That they did so
despite all the obstacles
they put on the path to this
finding is nearly incredible,
and directly bespeaks the
magnitude of adverse effects
of meat and processed
meat intake on health."
Based on their meta-analyses
of large cohorts,
dietary patterns with, again,
just a moderate reduction
in red and processed
meat consumption
were associated with
lower total mortality by 13%,
lower cardiovascular
disease mortality by 14%,
lower cancer mortality by 11%,
and a 24% reduced
risk of type 2 diabetes.
We spend tens of billions of dollars
a year trying to tweak risk factors
by about this magnitude.
And this one intervention,
a reduction in meat consumption,
appears to do all those
things at the same time.
I mean, there are statin drugs
that can reduce heart disease risk,
but actually increase risk
for type 2 diabetes,
and have little effect on cancer.
I mean if there was a drug that
did as much for your health,
it would be a multi-billion-
dollar blockbuster.
The chair of Nutrition at Harvard
estimates a moderate reduction
in red meat consumption could
prevent 200,000 deaths per year.
Now the meat panel can call that
a very small effect if they want to,
but I imagine it's no small effect
to those 200,000 families.
The numbers they found are on
par with the amount of cancer
and heart disease attributable
to second-hand smoke,
and based on the same kind
of studies, population studies.
It's not like they randomized people
to sit in smoky rooms all day
for a couple years.
But no rational person who
looks at the public health data
around the effectiveness of
smoke-free zones would argue
that people should continue exposing
themselves to secondhand smoke.
So why do the same for red
meat and processed meat?
The smoking analogy is
actually a good one.
Imagine researchers select
studies with extremely small
between-group differences
in the number of cigarettes
smoked per week.
They avoid any studies that
actually compare smoking
to non-smoking, i.e.,
meat-eating to vegetarian.
They find that despite the
small differences in exposure,
there is still a clear
and consistent benefit
to smoking less.
They then apply methods
of grading the evidence
that strongly favor randomized
trials over all other methods.
Since there are few, if any,
randomized trials of smoking,
they conclude that they
have very low confidence
in the reliability of
their own findings.
On that basis, they
publish guidelines
recommending that the public
simply continue to smoke.
After all, they reason, people
who smoke like smoking.
That really does sum up the
Annals papers in a nutshell.
That reminds me of a quote from
a famous paper published in 1958,
compiling all the most
poignant evidence
linking smoking and lung cancer,
after coming up against those
same charges of inadequate proof.
This quote could just as well
have been written about the
state of science on meat today:
If the mountain of evidence
they found had been made on
some new agent, to which
hundreds of millions of adults
had not already been addicted,
and on one which did
not support a large industry,
skilled in the arts
of mass persuasion,
the evidence for the
hazardous nature of the agent
would be generally regarded
as beyond dispute.
Don’t want to
die prematurely?
The final story
in our series
might help you avoid
doing just that.
According to the Global
Burden of Disease Study,
diets high in processed meat,
like bacon, ham, hot dogs,
lunch meat, sausage,
may kill off more than
100,000 people every year,
mostly due to heart disease,
but also cancer and diabetes,
resulting in millions
of healthy years of life lost
every year around the world.
And it doesn't take much. The Union
of Concerned Scientists estimated
that if Americans could cut
down to an ounce a week,
thousands of annual cancer
deaths could be averted.
But that's on a population scale.
How can we better understand
our individual risk?
Though the NutriRECS panel in
the Annals of Internal Medicine
meat papers I've done
the last few videos about,
discarded their own findings,
using their numbers, a reduction
in red and processed meat
consumption is associated
with a 13% lower risk
of premature death.
What exactly does that mean?
Like what does a 13%
increased risk of death mean?
To get a better handle on it, let me
introduce the concept of microlives.
Acute risks, such as riding a
motorbike or going skydiving,
may result in an accident.
A good way to compare such risks
is with a unit known as a Micromort,
defined as a 1-in-a-million
chance of sudden death.
I did a really fascinating
video about it recently.
However many risks we take
don't kill you straight away.
Think of all the lifestyle frailties
we get warned about,
such as smoking, drinking, eating
badly, not exercising, and so on.
So the microlife aims to make all
these chronic risks comparable
by showing how much life we lose on
average when we're exposed to them.
A microlife is defined as
30 minutes of your life expectancy.
Why is that?
Well, someone in their 20s, a 22-year
old man or a 26-year old woman,
may have, on average,
about 57 years left.
That's about 20,000 days, or 500,000
hours, or a million half hours.
Aha! So that's how
they define a microlife:
a reduction of one of the million
half hours we may have left.
Here are some things
that would, on average,
cost a 30-year-old man one microlife.
Smoking two cigarettes,
drinking two pints of beer,
or every day they live
11 pounds overweight.
See how helpful this can be
in terms of comparing risks.
So drinking a pint of strong beer
cuts your life expectancy short
as much as smoking one cigarette.
If it's unthinkable to you to have
so little respect for your own health
that you'd light up twice a day,
maybe one cigarette in the morning
and one at night, then it
should be just as unthinkable
being 11 pounds overweight.
Alternately you can compare
life-extending behavior.
For example, eating at least five
servings of fruits and veggies a day
may add an average of four years
onto your lifespan for men
and three years for women.
That's up to twice as beneficial
as exercising every day.
But check it out.
Exercise for 20 minutes,
and you add an hour to
your life, two microlives.
So for all those who say they
don't have time to exercise,
it's like a 3 to 1
return on investment.
Give 20 minutes of your
life to get 60 minutes of life.
Beyond that, there's a bit
of diminishing returns, butÂ
exercise an hour a day and get
back more time than you put in.
Okay, so what about the meat?
Each burger is associated
with the loss of a microlife.
So it's as if each burger were
taking 30 minutes off your life.
So lifespan-wise, one burger
appears equal to two cigarettes.
If it wouldn't occur to you
to light up at lunch,
maybe you should choose
the bean burrito instead.
And processed meat
is even worse.
There's a couple of
equivalent ways you could say it.
Imagine two people who
are identical in every way,
except that one eats around
50 grams of processed meat a day,
which is like one large sausage or
hot dog, or a few strips of bacon,
and the other eats none.
Eating that single serving
of processed meat every day
is expected to take about two
years off the length of your life.
Two years less with your
loved ones, your grandkids,
your spouse, two
more years of mourning.
Or you could think about
it on a day-to-day basis.
Eating a baloney or
ham sandwich every day,
just two slices of deli meat,
is expected to take around
one hour off your life each day.
Don't think there's ever
enough hours in the day?
Well, you may have
effectively one less
depending on what
you pack for lunch.
Alternatively, you could think
about it in terms of "effective age."
Eating 50 grams of processed meat
a day is expected to add around
two years onto your "effective age,"
meaning basically give you
the annual chance of dying
of someone two years older.
In summary, wrote the chair of
Nutrition at Harvard and colleagues,
the NutriRECS meat
recommendations suffer from
important methodological
limitations and involve
misinterpretations
of nutritional evidence.
To improve human - and
planetary health as a side bonus -
dietary guidelines should continue
to emphasize dietary patterns
low in red and processed meats,
and high in minimally processed
plant foods such as fruits, vegetables,
whole grains, nuts, and legumes -
beans, split peas,
chickpeas, and lentils.
Let me end with a quote
from Dr. Dean Ornish
about the Annals meat papers
that suggested people should
continue to eat meat
with abandon.
His Lifestyle Heart Trial
was one of the many studies
the meat panel ignored. It
showed that a plant-based diet
and lifestyle program could
reverse the progression
of even severe
coronary heart disease,
the #1 killer of men and women.
The control group actually made
modest reductions in meat
comparable to those
in the Annals review
and showed continued worsening
of their atherosclerosis.
"I take solace," Ornish said,
"in knowing that the light
"drives out the darkness.
"But, these days, the light
has to be very bright indeed.
"Caveat emptor.
Don't be fooled.
"Your life may depend on it."
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.